<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Considerations offered to all the corporations of England well worth their observation, containing seasonable advice to them in their future elections of burgesses to serve in Parliament, merely in relation to, and so far forth only as such elections affect trade, and are, as will appear hereby, the main cause of its present great decay.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34348</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5912</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25353</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08939975</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08939975</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42013</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34348)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42013)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1281:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Considerations offered to all the corporations of England well worth their observation, containing seasonable advice to them in their future elections of burgesses to serve in Parliament, merely in relation to, and so far forth only as such elections affect trade, and are, as will appear hereby, the main cause of its present great decay.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Cademan,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:42013:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Conſiderations Offered to all the CORPORATIONS OF ENGLAND, Well worth their <hi>OBSERVATION,</hi> Containing ſeaſonable advice to them in their future Elections OF BURGESSES To Serve in PARLIAMENT, Merely in Relation to, and ſo far forth only, as ſuch Elections affect Trade, and are, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear hereby, the main cauſe of its preſent great decay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Cademan,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Popes</hi>-Head, in the New-Exchange in the <hi>Strand,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:42013:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42013:2"/>
            <head>CONSIDERATIONS Offered to all the CORPORATIONS OF ENGLAND, <hi>Well worth their Obſervation, containing ſeaſonable Advice to them in their future Elections of B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGESSES to ſerve in</hi> PARLIAMENT, <hi>merely in relation to, and ſo far forth only, as ſuch Elections affect Trade, and are, as will appear hereby, the main Cauſe of its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Decay.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>EXperience does ſufficiently aſſure every Trading-man in this Kingdom, that there is a great and general decay of Trade, but the true Reaſon of this decay is known to few, and they very likely who do perceive it, having little or no Intereſt by it, are little or not all concerned to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy it; divers cauſes are aſſigned by divers men, according to their different Intereſt and Principles; the Divine charges it upon the ſinful lives of men, for which God has brought this, and threatens other yet ſeverer Judgments, and he is not altogether miſtaken, it being on all hands confeſt, that for the ſins of a Nation are Gods Judgments upon it, but as the deſign of theſe ſheets is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into ſecond and cauſes merely humane, I ſhall paſs over this firſt, with this Obſervation only, that if that were the only reaſon, as the ſins of the Nation are general, and common to all Orders and Degrees of men, the Judgments for thoſe ſins would be ſo too; but here is a heavier Portion upon one part, of the land then upon the reſt, and they who are moſt afflicted, are not perhaps the greateſt Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>To keep therefore within my bounds and to my firſt purpoſe of humane cauſes; that your factious Schiſmaticks (thoſe Enemies of God and the King) who hate and miſlike the Government only becauſe they have no ſhare in it, (and who fearing the pretence of Religion too ſtale a cheat, are glad to lay hold on any) are they who moſt cry out for the decay of Trade, tho they have leaſt reaſon ſo to do, ſince I ſhall make it appear anon they are the main cauſe of it, is viſible to all men, theſe impute that decay to the miſcarriages in Government; and whilſt their reſtleſs Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits (which ſtill long for the Fleſh-pots of their old Egypt in which the true <hi>Iſrael</hi> was by them enſlaved) are afraid too openly to declare againſt the Government, they do the utmoſt to undermine what they dare not directly aſſault, in commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſlily inſinuating the good daies of the late times, the Plenty, Power, Riches and Reputation of their dear Commonwealth; Thus labouring to create ſome diſturbance, that in the troubled waters they may fiſh for themſelves, and catch once more ſome ſhare in the Government which God and Nature have not formed, the King called, nor their own Abilities qualified them for.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:42013:3"/>
            <p>I come now to the true Cauſe, which as I have already ſaid, is cheifly in and from them who moſt complain: If Trade have not run in its old current; if Manufactors of all ſorts are brought ſo low, that Workmen can ſcarce be paid ſo as to live, and their Maſters get bread at the ſame time; If through this abatement of the value of Manufactures, men are ſo far diſcouraged from making them, that thouſands of men are thereby without employ; Men become averſe to the breading up their Children to Trades, by which they are not likely to get a Livelyhood, and Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as backward in taking Youth into their ſervice, when they have not a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of work enough to anſwer the charges of their Servants and their own Pains; the great reaſon of all this decay is, that Trade is not in that eſteem it was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the cauſe of the decreaſe of that eſteam is plain, becauſe it has not of late years had the advantages and encouragements it once had, and which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt by the Laws and Conſtitutions of the Kingdom it ought ſtill to have.</p>
            <p>Theſe diſcourages and diſadvantages of Trade, the true cauſes of its decay, are no leſs truly the effects of the undue Elections of Members to ſerve in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in which theſe ill affected Gentlemen have for theſe laſt fifty years, had a far greater Intereſt than the reſt of men who had voices in Elections; I call the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons undue, becauſe I find them directly againſt the plain words and ſenſe of ſuch Statutes as direct Elections.</p>
            <p>'Tis well known of late years, the houſe of Commons has been filled with Gentlemen, whoſe Ignorance of, and unconcern for Trade, has by degrees brought it to the condition it is now in; and the end I propoſe to my ſelf in this, is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince all Corporations, that it is their duty and intereſt in the elections hereafter, to chooſe ſuch men, who live and ſubſiſt by Trade, and whoſe intereſts are of neceſſity to riſe and fall as that does; that it is their duty will appear from the Acts af Parliament, and that it is their intereſt alſo, will I hope be made pretty plain from what I ſhall hereafter ſet down.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>7 H.</hi> 4. Ch. 15. 11 <hi>H.</hi> 4. Ch. 1. 1 <hi>H.</hi> 5. Ch. 1. 8 <hi>H.</hi> 6. Ch. 7. 10. <hi>H.</hi> 6. Ch. 2. 23 <hi>H.</hi> 6. Ch. 15.</note>There are ſeveral Statutes concerning Elections, as you will find them ſet down in the Margent, the firſt of theſe directs the time and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of giving notice in the County of an Election to be; the ſecond confirms the firſt, Fines the Sheriff who ſhall Act contrary to it in one hundred pounds; the third I ſhall ſpeak of laſt; the fourth appoints every Knight of the Shire that ſhall be choſen to have forty ſhilling a year at leaſt of freehold in the County where he ſhall be choſen, and to be reſident and dwelling in the ſame County; the fift obliges every man who ſhall have a voice in the election of a Knight of the Shire, to have likewiſe forty ſhillings a year, and to be dwelling in the ſame County; the ſixth provides againſt falſe returns, and appoints Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties on the Sheriffs in that caſe: The third which is moſt to the preſent purpoſe, confirming former Statutes, appoints what men ſhall be choſen Burgeſſes, and how qualified for the Election, which being ſo material and neceſſary for all men to know, I have thought good to ſet it down in its own words, the rather for that it is very ſhort.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>H.</hi> 5. Ch. 1.</note> Firſt that the Statutes of the Election of Knights of the Shires to come to the Parliament, be holden and kept in all points, adjoyning to the ſame, that the Knights of the Shires, which from henceforth ſhall be choſen in every Shire, be not choſen, unleſs they be reſident within the Shire where they ſhall be choſen, the day of the date of the Writ of the Summons of the Parliament: And that the Knights and Eſquires, and other which ſhall be Chooſers of thoſe Knights of the Shires, be alſo reſident within the ſame Shires in manner and form as is aforeſaid: and moreover it is Ordained and Eſtabliſh'd, that the Citizens and Burgeſſes of the Cities and Boroughs, be choſen Men Citizens and Bugeſſes reſident dwelling and Free in the ſame Cities and Boroughs, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in any wiſe.</p>
            <p>Thus far the Statute which is very ſhort and very plain: Here the King with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42013:3"/> his Parliament obſerving how at their time Gentlemen Freeholders were ſometimes returned for Boroughs, who had Intereſts of their own to manage, and theſe being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to thoſe of Tradeſmen, whoſe Burgeſſes they were, they were not like to favour theſe againſt themſelves, nor to take that care of Trade as was requiſite for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good, of which, and of the ways and means of improving it, they were wholly Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered by King and Parliament, to prevent the growing miſcheif, they did very ſeaſonably apply that early remedy of this act of Parliament, obliging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Corporations to chooſe Repreſentatives among themſelves of their own Cities and Boroughs, inhabiting and dwelling among them, and ſure this was done with as great Wiſdom as Juſtice; for ſince the deſign of Burgeſſes from every Corporation was (and ſtill is) that each City and Borough might have ſome body on their behalfs preſent in Parliament, well verſed in their ways and means of dealing, beſt acquainted with their Greivances, and conſequently beſt able to repreſent them; that ſo through the endeavours of every Burgeſes in particular, the Miſchiefs and Greivances of every part being made known, by thoſe who beſt knew them, the whole Nation might be preſerved and its Intreſts advanced; I do not ſee nor can conceive how any man can be preſumed better qualifyed to anſwer theſe ends, than ſuch men as the Statute directs, <hi>viz.</hi> Citizens and Burgeſſes reſident, dwelling and Free in the ſame Cities and Boroughs and in no other wiſe; and ſure for any number of men in any Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration to ſet up a ſtranger for the Election, is a bold liberty they aſſume to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of diſpenſing with Acts of Parliament, and that in a matter of the higheſt nature and conſequence imaginable; it is impoſing their ſenſe upon the Nation, and preferring their own private opinion to the Supream Wiſdom and Judgment of the Kingdom, the King and his two Houſes; and this I think is ſufficient to ſhew them their plain, eaſie and neceſſary duty in Elections. I come now to ſhew that it is their Intereſt alſo; where it might be enough to tell them that the ſame reaſons which induced at firſt the making that Act of Parliament, do at this day oblige in point of intereſt all men to the juſt execution of it: It is a known rule, <hi>ceſſante cauſa ceſſat ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus;</hi> ſo <hi>vice verſa,</hi> ſhould the ſame cauſes continuing be attended with the like effects; and indeed I ſhould be glad that any man would ſhew me, how according to this Statute moſt of our late Elections be made out: how by your Statute is a Gentleman of the Temple a fit Member for <hi>Worceſtor</hi> or <hi>Taunton?</hi> or how a very worthy Knight reſident and dwelling in <hi>Southampton</hi> Square (tho otherwiſe of very great abilities) ſufficiently qualified for a Burgeſs of <hi>Plymouth?</hi> how theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men I ſay (tho never ſo learned in all other things) can be ſuppoſed to underſtand perfectly the particular Intereſt of Cities and Towns, in which perhaps they nere ſet foot but at Elections? or what reaſon Tradeſmen have to hope or promiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that Strangers (being Gentlemen, whoſe Intereſts if they run not directly counter to, are yet very different from theirs who chooſe them) ſhould be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned for their good (tho in oppoſition to their own,) than men of their own body, obliged by the ſame Intereſts, and therefore moved by the ſame conſiderations, is not within my underſtanding: The miſchiefs and evils in the Body Politick do thus far reſemble the natural body, that to know and well underſtand the diſtemper is a good ſtep to the cure of it, this is by all men allowed; ſo likewiſe that the knowledge a Phyſician has of the conſtitution of a body with reaſon prefers him to abler means in the cure, as moſt likely to remove the evil, common experience demonſtrates daily: This might be ſufficient to ſhew that tis the intereſt of Tradeſmen, to ſend Members choſen out of themſelves; yet to make this more plain, to matter of Reaſon I will add matter of Fact, and ſhew them how by neglect of this duty in their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections they have already actually received much damage.</p>
            <p>1. What has the Houſe of Commons, being full of Gentlemen, done, as for inſtance (not to run back into times, which it were to be wiſht were as abſolutly forgot as the Guilt of them is forgiven) in 1660? It was neceſſary to improve the revenue of the Crown, they did it by eaſing themſelves and laying the burthen upon the Trading part of the people.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:42013:4"/>
            <p>The Court of Wards and Liveries, Tenures in Capite and by Knights ſervice, were one of the goodlieſt Jewels in the Crown, a high and vaſt Prerogative it was, and ſuch a one, by means whereof the Kings of <hi>England</hi> had a ſtrange hand over all the Gentry, by the great Intereſt they had in all their houſes as well over the perſons of their Children as their Eſtates; yet this Prerogative extended but to them, Tradeſmen were not at all concerned, this therefore they thought fit to remove, but that the Crown might be no loſer (as there was no reaſon it ſhould) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was to be found out <hi>equivalent,</hi> the Exciſe, which juſt before had been given for the Kings Life, was thought ſitteſt, and was accordingly ſettled upon the Crown in Fee. <note place="margin">12. Ca. 2di. <hi>Ch. 24.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>II.</hi> The taking away theſe Courts has been as Prejudicial to the Yeomanry, as it has been uſeful to the Gentry, who before, of Intereſt were obliged to make their Farms leſs, and to let long Leaſes at reaſonable Rates; but now they erect great Farms which few are able to Rent, and Rack the poor Tenants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>III.</hi> All the Aſſeſſments and Revenues of the Crown, are cheifly paid by the middle ſort of People, as Tenths and firſt Fruits from the Clergy, Cuſtoms by Merchants, Exciſe by Brewers, Chimney-mony by Tenants, Freeholders paying nothing certain to the Crown, which is a great diſadvantage to the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding People; that Freeholders are not obliged to ſome Proportion, at leaſt in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IV.</hi> Upon a Preſumption of raiſing the Product of <hi>England,</hi> many Laws have been neglected, which would be highly for the intereſt of the Trading ſort of People, and ſome Laws have been made directly contrary to their Intereſt, which is no wonder, when amongſt the Law-givers there are ſo few (if any) that either underſtand what may prejudice or advance Trade, or if they do, through ſelf Intereſt, Politickly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble that Knowledge, of this ſort are all thoſe Laws which give leave for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of the growth of <hi>England</hi> without Manufacturing: Secondly moſt of thoſe Laws prohibit the growth of other Countries, which if Trading were free, we might with great advantage purchaſe with our own Manufactures, of this kind there is a very late one, the Iriſh Bill, which enriching only a few in the Weſt of <hi>England,</hi> is out of every houſe-keepers way in <hi>London,</hi> and moſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, twenty ſhillings a year for every perſon in his Family, beſides the diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of our Artificers in Exchange of Manufacture, and our Iriſh Merchant in Exchange of Mony.</p>
            <p>Before I paſs further, I muſt needs here mention one great damage the Crown it ſelf ſuſtains by this Bill; for the Victualing the Navy ſtands his Majeſty each pound of Beef once as much again as his Neighbours the French and Dutch, to whom the Iriſh (being forbidden <hi>England</hi>) are forced to ſell their Cattle at a very low rate; thus the King loſes, the City loſes, all <hi>Ireland</hi> or a good part of it ſuffers, when beſides the French and Dutch, a few Weſt Country Gentlemen and their Tenants only gain by it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>V.</hi> There are many Laws which would be of very great uſe for the Publick Intereſt, which upon the ſame account are neglected and laid aſide; as firſt the moſt excellent Statute of the fifth of the Queen, <hi>Ch.</hi> 5. The very title of which were ſufficient to recommend it, it is an Act touching politick Conſtitutions for the maintenance of the Navy; in this Statute amongſt other things, that great and wiſe Princeſs, and as true a Proteſtant as the beſt of them that diſtinguiſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by the Name, makes ſeveral Proviſions for the encreaſe of Shipping, and Saylers, appointing them certain Fiſh days, by which means they might be encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged through the certainty of a Market for Fiſh, to build Veſſels, bring up and employ Seamen, and for want of which, thoſe few that do now uſe Fiſhing, carry it into other Countries, where they are ſure of a Market, ſo that we find by Experience that Fiſh is cheaper in other Countries of <hi>Europe,</hi> than it is here in <hi>England,</hi> though that Fiſh be taken upon our Coaſt and by our Country-men. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly Fleſh would be at a more reaſonable rate, if that Prodigious quantity were not each day devoured, and for which we are look'd upon as ſuch Gluttons by the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42013:4"/> world, even to become a by-word among the Nations, for who has not heard it ſaid that <hi>London</hi> muſt needs be a ſtrange Beaſt, that in ſix Months conſumes more fleſh than all <hi>Spain</hi> in ſeven years, and this was another end of that Statute.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VI.</hi> The Laws ought to be revived which preſerves the Property of the Trading Corporation, and thoſe which regard Aliens, not that at this time, when the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of King and Council think fit in ſo extraordinary an occaſion to receive and encourage them to uſe their Trades, I preſume to offer any thing further than that the Statute, whereby they cannot work, but as retained by Engliſh, nor take o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apprentices than Engliſh, ſaving their own Children, be at that time look'd well after; for that by ſuch means, theſe Aliens might freely Trade, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit be ſhared between them and the Engliſh.</p>
            <p>7. The Laws againſt Hawkers ought to be revived, by whom great abuſes are committed; Wares are ill made and Trade brought low, all which matters now ſo heavy on Tradeſmen would be remedied, if ſo in their Elections they perſued the Act of Parliament, and made choiſe of ſuch men as were ſenſible of ſuch grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and were obliged as well of Intereſt as in Juſtice to redreſs them.</p>
            <p>There are likewiſe many things very advantageous and beneficial that might be paſt into Laws, if ſuch Elections were,</p>
            <p>1. As firſt, that Freeholders ſhould conſtantly bear an equal ſhare in Payments to the Crown with the Trading People; that would Enable the King to force a Trade abroad, and encourage Manufactures at home.</p>
            <p>2. That a Regiſter might be Eſtabliſh'd to prevent Cheats, which fall moſt on Tradeſmen, and the many trivial Suits in Law, upon ſeveral and inconſiderable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts; a Bleſſing not to be hoped for as long as Lawyers fill the Houſe.</p>
            <p>3. That all Linnen cloth under the value of 3 <hi>s.</hi> an Ell might be prohibited, and a valuable Tax ſet upon our own Manufactured Cloth, to make up the loſs the Crown will receive by that Prohibition: This would employ a Million of People, and if the Work were carried on by a publick Stock, it would in three years time abate as much in the Poors Book, as the firſt advanced Stock would amount to.</p>
            <p>4. That many Perſons having little or no Eſtate, (who live at a rate much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their Ranks and Fortunes, whereby the Tradeſmen of whom they take up muſt needs be loſers) may be obliged to take to ſome honeſt Employment.</p>
            <p>5. That mony lent upon Land-ſecurity, ſhould not receive above <hi>4l. 10s. per Cent</hi> and mony upon Perſonal-ſecurity, be at <hi>8l. per Cent.</hi> The preſent equality of Intereſt mony, without reſpect to the difference of the ſecurity, having this diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, that <hi>6l. per Cent.</hi> being more profitable than the Land it ſelf at 20. years Purchaſe, men chooſe rather to lend upon Land, than Purchaſe it; hence ariſe Mortgages, whereby ſo many have been cheated; where if this remedy were had, men would chooſe to buy outright, and Fraud prevented.</p>
            <p>From theſe Conſiderations I preſume it is by this time pretty plain, that it is the Intereſt of all the Corporations in <hi>England,</hi> to make choice in their Elections here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, of Tradeſmen of their own reſpective Corporations; it being as abſurd as injurious to truſt all the Trade of <hi>England,</hi> in the hands of men, who neither truly underſtand it, nor are concerned to improve and advance it, it being clearly the Intereſt of Freeholders, that the number of Tradeſmen increaſe, though not their Fortunes, that Tradeſmen be many and poor.</p>
            <p>There is no doubt but after the making of the Statute of <hi>H. 5th.</hi> Citizens and Tradeſmen were returned to ſerve in Parliament; and 'tis very clear that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why that Cuſtom has been diſcontinued, was by reaſon of the charges each City and Borough was at in paying their Members, which made them give ear to thoſe who voluntarily profered their ſervice, tho they have dearly paid for it ſince: ſurely there is ſcarce any Corporation ſo poor, but amongſt them may be found two men of ſuch Fortunes as does enable them to bear the expence of that ſervice, tho otherwiſe the paying of Members is by far the leſs evil, conſidering what bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens have been laid upon them by a houſe of Commons made up of Gentlemen and Lawyers.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:42013:5"/>
            <p>The greateſt Strengh and Riches of <hi>England,</hi> were formerly in the hands of the middle ſort of People, and is not yet ſo far Alienated, but that it may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieved, if care be taken to make due Elections; without which the wealth of the Nation will quickly be engroſſed into a few hands, and what ways or means men then ſhall have to raiſe their Foruunes by Diligence and Induſtry, every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Judgement can ſatisfie it ſelf.</p>
            <p>From theſe late Elections it has followed, that the Intereſts of Corporations have been neglected, their greivances unregarded, whilſt ſo many learned Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, have thought every thing leſs than the whole Kingdom at a lump, too mean for their Conſideration.</p>
            <p>The bare name of a States-man, or Stickler, has of late prefer'd many men to Elections, and they have held themſelves obliged to make good the opinion their Electors had entertained of them; ſo that one may ſay every ſingle Burgeſs has of late, been not ſo much the Repreſentative of a Corporation, as of the whole Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon men give to excuſe the great neglect of the Intereſt of Corporations is very plauſible; Corporations, ſay they, are but little Members of the body politick, of which the State is the head; if that be diſeaſed and its humours not purged, the ſeveral Members will be affected, and that I allow; But whether the ways and meaſures lately perſued with ſo much zeal and paſſion, be the propereſt means to purge what ill humours are in the head, ſo as to reſtore health and vigour to every Member, is a Queſtion. May we not reaſonably think, that if every Member would ſtudy the particular advantages of that County, City, Borough, he ſerves for, make it his buſineſs to enquire well into their Intereſts, and repreſent their real greivances, and each in their turns get the concurrence of the whole houſe to the remedying thereof; may we not think, I ſay, that this way of curing and comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every Member ſeverally (which would produce in the end, eaſe and ſafety to all) might do the buſineſs every whit as well? yet this is not to be expected, whilſt by a monſtrous miſtruſt of the honeſty or ability of own our fellow Citizens, (not like <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> who has wiſely at all times preſerved that great and important right of ſending Members of her own) we accept of Gentlemen, whom (if but for their eager deſire of the employment, being Strangers to us) we might very reaſonably ſuſpect to have ſome other and further ends and deſigns by the Election, than our Intereſts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns; For I cannot be brought to believe, that a Gentleman, one whom I have never obliged, of different Intereſts from me, will ſpend a thouſand pounds to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry an Election, merely to ſerve mine: How unlikely this is, and unreaſonable ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be to beleive it, yet we ſwallow the Pill, and are as fond of chooſing them, as they are glad to be choſen; Thus whilſt we cry out Liberty and Property, full of needleſs and imaginary fears and apprehenſions from higher Powers, we our ſelves are the greateſt betrayers of our Rights and Liberties, whilſt we raſhly and unadviſedly, truſt them and our Religion in the hands of men, whoſe Principles in Religion, Maxims of State, ſecret grudges and diſtaſts at the Government up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on private accounts, we as little underſtand as they do our true Intereſts.</p>
            <p>And now whilſt we may Lawfully do our ſelves Juſtice, to neglect it, and promiſe it to our ſelves from other men, is ſurely great indiſcretion: The miſcheifs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences of undue Elections, are I hope made out, the burthen that lies ſo heavy on Tradeſmen moſt plain; what is wanting to perfect the happineſs of the Nation, and the means to arrive at it ſet down; and all this to be done with much eaſe and ſecurity; If therefore the Conſiderations of duty cannot move men to ſtand their own Friends, at leaſt let the dear Argument of ſelf Intereſt be as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent in this, as it uſually is upon all other occaſions.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
